so this is a suitor maybe
for monks really a discussion for monks
maybe they would understand it a bit
more but in any case
it's called one in training
so the buddha says amongst this
recitation of more than 150 training rules
of more than 150 training rules
he means patimoka comes
up every fortnight in reference to which
sons of good families desiring the goal
train themselves
there are these three trainings under
which all that is gathered
which three the training in heightened
virtue the training in heightened
mind and the training in heightened
discernment these are the three trainings under
these are the three trainings under
which all that is gathered
so there is a case where a monk is
wholly accomplished fully accomplished in
accomplished fully accomplished in
virtue
moderately accomplished in samadhi
and modern moderately accomplished in
discernment with reference to the lesser and minor
with reference to the lesser and minor
training rules
he falls into offenses and rehabilitates
himself he confesses them and so he's not
he confesses them and so he's not
ignoring yeah
why is that because i so
why is that because i have not declared
that to be a disqualification in this
these circumstances meaning
being wholly accomplished virtue it
doesn't compromise that yeah
but as for the training rules that are
basic to the holy life
and proper to the holy life he's one of
permanent virtue one of steadfast virtue having
virtue one of steadfast virtue having
undertaken him he trains in reference to
the training rules
and with the ending of the first three
fetters he's a stream
winner a social planner never again
destined for the states of uh
woe certain headed for self awakening
and it goes on through that through the
different levels of attainment all the
way up to
arahan shapley on the basis of that yeah
accomplished in fully accomplished
virtue fully accomplished in
uh mind what does it mind in mind high
tide in in yeah that would follow the same
in in yeah that would follow the same
sense that the you know the
the mountain stream would fill out the
bottom pools that they were going to
overfill and fill up the bottom
eventually and eventually even the sea
would be filled up and at the end of
that suitor he says those who are partially
suitor he says those who are partially
accomplished attain apart those who are
whole fully accomplished attain the full thing
fully accomplished attain the full thing
the training rules i tell you are not in
vain yeah
yeah and that's the that's the important
part that the rules that are essence of the
that the rules that are essence of the
training are basically the eight
precepts
whenever we talk about you know the wise
man of the past the virtuous people the
past it's the eighth precepts of these
it's the eighth precepts of these
principles then you can have many other
rules in in in the monastic venue you
have many other rules but they're all
kind of
within that the one the rules of matter
then you have the circumstantial social
rules and so on minor rules
but the ones that matter for the
training are basically the ones that are
around lust
aversion distraction and delusion that's
it
so yes that's meant for the monks but
actually even a layperson if they become
accomplished in eight precepts
can expect the same heightened mind and
height and discernment
i mean many lay people in the sutas were
were gummies they were teaching monks
they knew monks because they were so
developed and so so what is that their development
and so so what is that their development
is it
the technical letter of the rule you
know prescribed by the contemporary
tradition what is it where is it so what is what
what is it where is it so what is what
is that what
what is that accomplishment what does it
make accomplished
is he knowing the latter of every rule
and looking for every technicality
or knowing the state of mind and
intention behind your actions
which is closer so whenever people are
latching on to technicalities and the letter of
on to technicalities and the letter of
the rules
it's when the intention for the state of
mind is either obscured not taking
is either obscured not taking
responsibility for or
blatantly just to be avoided
so you don't feel responsible because
this is the tradition that i follow
this is the rules that i follow this is
the latter that i follow and
i don't think i don't need to think for
myself and because of that you can
follow such rules in such manner
for 100 years have like the full
ordination the encourage the cruel
and still not be accomplished in virtue
and that's exactly what silva parma says
taking on
um virtue as a sense of external duty
for which you're not allowing yourself
to feel
responsible for internally and
why would the person not allow
themselves to be responsible for that
because the moment you become
responsible you become liable to doubt
so that's exactly why silabata paramasa
is bundled with a factor of doubt
if you actually manage to break yourself
away from the dependence on the external
letter and take responsibility for the virtue
and take responsibility for the virtue
you will creating a basis for overcoming
the fact of doubt
but if you don't allow yourself to step
away from it in that correct sense in
that correct direction
you will never overcome that because the
reason why the duty is imposed
by yourself to yourself is so the doubt
cannot arise
and you often see that when when when a
mind that's dependent on the letter
somebody points out that that letter
might be wrong they're
overwhelmed i mean we witness it many
times overwhelmed with the existential doubt
overwhelmed with the existential doubt
because they realize everything leading
up to that
was based on that letter saying what it
says so i didn't feel responsible for
yet now somebody just questions that
they don't even prove
that the letter of your rule is wrong
they just start questioning
and you are shaking
and if that doesn't concern you means
you you lack even basic authenticity
basic self-awareness and that's why
there is no right view for you
so you need to understand that that yes
you learn the letter of the rules
but depending how like how far you're
going to go into the letter of the rules
and why is it because i'm not really
still understanding the rule sure
go further is it no i understand the
rule but i want more technicalities to
prevent me from myself
and from my own mind oh you want to
avoid the practice
because that's where samadhi is as we
said before
things they want to overwhelm the mind
the monk doesn't let the mind being
overwhelmed that's his practice of
samadhi so you understood the rule you
so you understood the rule you
understand the eight precepts you
understand the ten priesthood you
understand 150 training rules
if you're not clear about some rule
you're clarified that's it
now you practice you practice in a way
by
keep making sure when you're about to
act you act according with those rules
or you have to call him with an ungreed
and aversion on delusion
uh if you break it you see where you
broke it you see why you broke it
and you don't need to depend on
technicality because you're always aware
of your intention behind the actions
and then somebody points out
technicality allows you this but it's
like it doesn't the state of mind
doesn't allow you to do that so if you
actually stop looking
if you start looking at the context of
the rules eight presets or 150 precepts
and maintain the context of the rules in
your mind there will be no loopholes for
you and there will be no need for the
and there will be no need for the
loopholes
if you start looking at the letter that
gets proliferated more and more and more
into this
definition of a sub definition of a sub
definition then all of it it will be about
then all of it it will be about
loopholes
it will be about things that are left
not addressed
and you know they come under the same
context but you have drifted away from
that context so much now
into these particulars that you lost the
sight of the forest pretty much
uh and that's exactly when when people
and monks
become technical well technically i'm
not breaking the rule and stuff it's
like what is the state of mind behind that
what is the state of mind behind that
action breed resolution
you are breaking the virtue end of story
there is no accomplishment in virtue
unless you take the virtue on that level
of the mind
but people confuse learning about the
rules learning about technicalities for
keeping the rules and keeping the
technicalities in other words they feel
justified in not taking it personally in
not taking responsibility for it
but projecting and keeping
responsibility on the level of well
that's the tradition
there's the authority that's how it's
been for hundreds of years doesn't
matter you can choose to accept the tradition
you can choose to accept the tradition
the traditional rules
the the traditional standards that's all
fine but even if you do so you still have to
but even if you do so you still have to
recognize that you're responsible for
that you're responsible for either choosing
you're responsible for either choosing
to interpret things for yourself for
rather choosing to follow
this commentary rather choosing to
follow someone else's interpretation or
someone else's tradition it's on you
nothing justifies you in choosing that
so in other words you need to recognize
that whether you you understand it for
whether you you understand it for
yourself directly or whether you follow
someone else's interpretation you need
to know
why you are doing it that needs to
be clear to you so if i ask you oh do
you keep the eight presets yes oh well
the fifth presets what's your standard
on it how do you understand
such and such circumstance and you tell
me well i follow the tradition of such
and such
teacher i i was like dog that's fine
why you should be able to tell me why do
you follow
that in other words how is that
way of like following that particular uh
interpretation or the rule or take on
the rule
how is that feeding your accomplishment
in virtue directly how is that connected
to it
you can't just say i follow because he's
a great teacher
well yeah but what is the benefit of
following that do you see that for
yourself or you're just going by mere reputation
or you're just going by mere reputation
and mere tradition and hearsay
which is you know the buddha said many
times something you shouldn't really do
unless you're very unwise so yeah follow
like you know clarify whatever else but
never feel justified on just oh well
i belong to this great tradition now and
these are our standards and that's the
end of the game there no
why why do i keep these standards do i
keep them
authentically individually personally
internally in which case i don't need
the tradition in the standards
because it's kept on this level not on
the level of traditional behavior
and that's how exactly what was said if
you actually accomplish yourself
on that level in that virtue where
you're not shying away from doubt
but willing to endure it clarifying the
context maintaining the context not
proliferating the rule to prevent you
from having doubt arise in your mind
again i will never do that again wait but it
i will never do that again wait but it
wasn't an offense it was not an issue
he wasn't even rooted in greed aversion
delusion but why am i doubting it
because that's what doubt is it's an
irrational mind a hindrance
that tries to throw you away tries to
make you act out of it
and here you are acting out of it
because now you're redefining and making
new rules so you will never do stuff
that you know was nothing wrong with
just because you doubted on account of
it and you never you don't know how to
deal with the doubt
so by taking the taking the virtue
wrongly you will not be able to deal
with the doubt because of which you'll
keep taking the virtue wrongly because
of which you can't deal with the doubt
exactly absolutely because there is no
accomplishment if you take the words rightly endure the
if you take the words rightly endure the
doubt don't act out of the doubt
sustain the context of the virtue no
because you know
you know what it is but the mind
pressures you to find out more look into
technique create this create that act
left left right
avoid prevent if you sustain that and
not act out of it
you will become accomplished in the
virtue and basically how did you do that
oh that's already the practice of
samadhi not moving in regard to the mind they
not moving in regard to the mind they
want to move it
and that's what the buddha said is just
if somebody's accomplished
at least in that basis three fatties
will have to be destroyed
you cannot not be a sotapanna if you
have taken virtue on that level
and endured it but you will certainly
not be a soda panna
if you've taken virtue on the level of
the external letter of the law the rule
the tradition the authority the agenda
the senior monk whatever else even if
they were right
by the way in the standards that they
laid upon you if you took it externally
there is no basis for your virtue to
actually take place
so it's like if you the first precept of
not harming not killing a living being
why do you keep that why is that wrong and
do you keep that why is that wrong and
if you don't know
why you cannot be accomplished well it's
just kind of circumstantially taking
that external rule
you learn them circumstantially you you
investigate them in circumstantially but
once you start keeping them no you need
to know for yourself like you need this
to
needs to be seen personally like why
this is not done why it's not good to do
this so that's the thing so you see what is
so that's the thing so you see what is
unwholesome what is wholesome
that is your discernment there clearer
that is that's what you're going to
start seeing you're going to start
seeing wholesome is wholesome and
wholesome is unwholesome because you're
seeing the roots of that which makes it
unwholesome what makes it wholesome
but you will not see that if if you just
block it and say well this is our
tradition this is my culture
this is what a buddhist person does he's
like well okay
and that's that's literally applicable
to every other religion
that level of ah i am such and such i
identify with that religion without
observance with that rule
i keep it no questions asked because it
makes sense
well exactly yeah because well all
questioning means you don't keep it no
question it means i want to know what i
keep so there's no there's no justification
so there's no there's no justification
for you assuming cynical reasons
for my questioning unless it's your own
cynical mind putting that over there
no i want to understand what i keep but
for many people even
questioning to understand what will make
you like do i need to keep this do i
want to keep this do i want to be a monk
do i want to practice
and that's something also they it makes
you unpleasant makes you doubtful
so you refuse to think about it you
refuse to question you just double down
this is my duty this is the tradition
and you double down on your own syllabus
the very first fatter because of which
as i said you can keep the eight presets
for 100 years and
and absolutely have no samadhi and
wisdom arising from it
if you if you look at the the beginning
of the
monastic order there were no rules
no of course why was clear yeah it was
not obscured
people knew exactly what behaviors were
in line with it and what behaviors
weren't yeah so and that that that basic you can
yeah so and that that that basic you can
boil it down to
don't do anything awesome know what a
wholesome issue
don't do it and that's why also as the
things sort of progressed
back in the buddhist time that whole
need for like you know a new monk would
have to spend like five years
training with senior monk somebody that
accepted him because yes an untrained
mind will start like you know will not
be able to necessarily even sustain the
right context
so you want to spend the first few years
learning that context but you don't want
to spend the first few years
just learning the the letter of the some
tradition that you got into without
actually understanding why you're doing
it or
developing that authentic recognition
that it's still up to you whether you
keep it or not and to what extent and
you want to see the intentions behind
your actions there
because that's often like okay so
basically even even that process of
learning for five years from a senior
monk has become like a mechanical letter
has become like a mechanical letter
of stuff you go through without actually
learning and without monk teaching you either so
and without monk teaching you either so
just for five years you're under
someone's like tutorship but
like tutorship but
in in in reality it's just basically
learning of
of that external form
uh external letter not being taught
responsibility behind
not being told how to see the
responsibility behind how to take it on
in which case you would you wouldn't
even need them
the further definitions of these rules
because you would be unable to ignore
the unwholesome intentions before you
act so you wouldn't act
that's the training but even training
has become like uh like a traditional
form in the same sense external on the level
in the same sense external on the level
of silabata paramasa
on the level of virtue
dead well yeah yeah it's it's it's just
like a dead matter in that sense yeah
but individually everybody can rekindle
it for themselves
if they actually exactly started in the
suttas reading the origin stories and so
on and you start seeing for you get you
getting that livable context and you
know it's about the state of mind it's
about the perception how i perceive it what i
the perception how i perceive it what i
choose to do it's not about you know
commentary of a subcommentary of a
subcommentary defining this is allowable
and then another commentary defining
that is not allowable
in me now spending nights in figuring
out who might be more
right than these two no where is my
attention rooted you got your answer
and on top of that not just that you got
the answer as to what is the right thing
to do
you also started accomplishing yourself
in virtue which is a basis for
sotopa so if you don't have the right view if
so if you don't have the right view if
you have not reached a few
fruits of stream entry it's because you
haven't been accomplishing virtue
and it's good news because now you know
what to do accomplish yourself in virtue
how do you do that by taking it
personally learning the rules sure learning
learning the rules sure learning
interpretations sure
but not relying on the word of the rule
the authority of interpretation of
tradition as this is why it's kept no
it's kept because i choose to keep it
and i choose to keep it because i see
direct relationship between that and
holds the mind
or not that and unholds the mind
and that will inevitably initially
certainly bring the doubt
bring that sense of oh so i could just
decide to not give exactly
and you're going to feel the weight of
keeping that
and that's how you become accomplished
but in also doing that
you will eventually begin to see which
rules are actually obsolete yes but you
are actually obsolete yes but you
wouldn't really worry about that you
wouldn't but you would
as a become you will become self-evident
exactly the minor rules will not affect him and
the minor rules will not affect him and
he will know that he'd still confess he
wouldn't have an issue
but sometimes the problem is if a person
is not accomplishing the virtue
and then get a sense of righteousness of
discovering of this what we are saying
and then they just try to form a new
tradition of dismissing all the
traditions and interpreting things for
yourself yeah in a same external manner of
yeah in a same external manner of
silabata paramasa
you don't need to change anything you
need to take things personally
and then what needs to be changed will
happen by itself
because you have the authentic mind you
have the accomplishment in virtue
samadhi is there what change occurs will
be the right change you wouldn't have to
do it
you wouldn't have to act out of it in
other words you would naturally
drift away from things that are
unsuitable traditions that are
unsuitable practices that are unsuitable
into the the the directions that are
suitable for the right view for this passion and
for the right view for this passion and
for everything else without needing to
make a big deal out of it
but you will become this self-righteous
impossible impossible impossible you would not
impossible impossible you would not
either become scared
you wouldn't be self-righteous trying to
change everybody but if everybody comes
after an account of it you wouldn't show
up because you know what's right
so you wouldn't need to change the
established external norms
but you wouldn't be afraid to challenge
them either because it's not rooted in
your conceit
it's rooted in recognition of what the
accomplishment of virtue is and the
right view
so if you were to question those things
you wouldn't just you know be on a
crusade to change though as i said
but if it comes up to it you wouldn't be
afraid of it
if circumstances bring it up you you
will have no issues
dealing with it and addressing it
in there's another suit as summoner
the buddha says a mandicant a monk
thus accomplished in virtue sees no
danger in any quarter in regards to their
in any quarter in regards to their
virtuous restraint
it is like a king who has defeated his
enemies he sees no danger from his
enemies in any
direction in that same way a monk
thus accomplished in virtue sees no
danger in any direction in regards to
their virtuous restraint when they have
this aggregate this domain of noble virtue
aggregate this domain of noble virtue
the scunder of noble virtue they
experience a blameless have happiness inside
a blameless have happiness inside
themselves
that is how a monk is accomplished in
virtue so the monk who has ceased to depend
so the monk who has ceased to depend
on the external circumstances external
authority external definitions
external rules external requirements
has become accomplished in virtue
because internal criteria
as in not i choose to interpret no
knowing right is right wrong is wrong wholesome
right is right wrong is wrong wholesome
is wholesome means knowing lust aversion
delusion sufficiently enough to always see it and
sufficiently enough to always see it and
not act out of it
you practice that you will become
accomplished in that and then it doesn't
matter the circumstance doesn't matter
what quarter
the the circumstances arrive at you from
what direction there is no danger
because you're not depending on that
so if somebody comes and starts
questioning a certain interpretation of
a letter of a rule it doesn't matter
because that's not what your virtue was
based on it was based on
you not doing anything out of intention
of greed aversion delusion
so even if somebody says look this all
these rules were actually
wrong uh they were written by somebody
later in
insert today they're not right makes no
difference and you would actually know that they
and you would actually know that they
were right even if somebody did add them
they'd added them rightly
because they're according to the
standard of dharma standard of
dispassion disenchantment non-greed non-aversion on
disenchantment non-greed non-aversion on
delusion
but for islam as you put the letter
first the external authority of silabata
the external authority of silabata
paramasa first
you will not see this because you're
refusing to take responsibility for it
and allow it to become internal because
it's unpleasant
the weight of it is unpleasant the the
the way the responsibility is unpleasant
the pressure is unpleasant the liability
to doubt is unpleasant
and you have to endure it developing of
samadhi is unpleasant
and same eight precepts for a lay person
saying that's why often the buddha would not
that's why often the buddha would not
even overly define
things because if the mind isn't hasn't
strayed from the right context
of non-greed non-aversion on delusion
recognizes that state of mind doesn't
act out of it regardless of what the
action might be
you don't need extra and extra layers of
of definitions and words and
interpretations and meanings because
the meaning is there the context is
there it's clear
so that's what practically eight
precepts are modern enough certainly for
anagami
in the lay setting for a monkey you'll
be another hunter accomplished to the
same virtue
the same thread i like the way it's
it's said like the he is
accomplished or attained in possesses
the aggregate of virtue the aggregate of
virtue
he created an aggregate yeah that now he
can recognize
he can recognize and he's encouraged to
recollect and dwell because it will
reinspire confidence and sense of safety
and gladness they will then bring
samadhi and so on to fulfillment
and clear understanding of what's what
what but not without it and that is
but not without it and that is
again that is the entire practice your
samadhi comes out of it
your pioneer comes out of it the more
you do it the more you perfect it
greed aversion delusion removed from
physical verbal and mental
that's what dhamma is so
start on the physical level and that is
your samadhi that is your panya that is
your practice towards
satapathy and higher
it's not found elsewhere it's not found
after it's right there and then
it's not done for just a short period of
time and then
that's one thing it's better to even
like if you if you oh
eight too much as a lay person take the
five precepts
for the rest of your life but not for
the weekend
this means you never really allow you
never even consider changing the order
of what's important to you sensuality is
important to you
so now you realize that yeah presets are
good and maybe i should do something
about it
but then you only do it like for two or
three days or five days
means oh you're just sort of
toying with it while at the same time
refusing to allow
the actual no centrality to be put
second and my precepts will now be first for
and my precepts will now be first for
the rest of my life
and that's important that's where he
undertakes the training of virtue you need to take
the training of virtue you need to take
it in that ultimate sense
not to this conditional i'll do it a bit
until i get meditation experience or
something no no
it's in that sense it's better to do
five presets but for the rest of your
life then to like no precepts and then
then to like no precepts and then
super austere level of celibacy for 10
days and then
boom no presets at all because that is
not accomplishing keeping
it's not accomplishing anything really
like i mean
you're obviously trying so that's a good
thing i suppose but
you want to recognize the gradual
training starts gradually
and starts in that responsible sense but
absolutely non-negotiable sense so he's like okay
non-negotiable sense so he's like okay
so what can i sustain
and what am i able to can i make this
determination for the rest of my life to to not kill
for the rest of my life to to not kill
cheat lie steal misconduct take
intoxicates and if if just that thought scares you
and if if just that thought scares you
oh i can't do this with
that you need to do that first before
you can even consider
direction of any practice whatsoever
because that is the practice
you considering that is the practice you
making yourself being able to determine
to keep the five pieces for the rest of
your life or aid priests for the rest of
us
is the beginning of your accomplishment
in virtue
it won't come up come come like it won't
result on its own somehow
because you got a you know a very very
very potent meditation method they will
now if you adhere to it
just create this virtue for you
another suitor called the restraint of
the patimoka
then a certain beku approached a blessed
one and asked him vulnerable sir it would be
and asked him vulnerable sir it would be
good if the blessed one would teach me
the dummy in briefs that having heard
the dhamma from the blessed one i might
dwell alone withdrawn diligent ardent and
alone withdrawn diligent ardent and
residue
and the buddha replies in that case beku
purify the very beginning of wholesome states
the very beginning of wholesome states
and what is the beginning of wholesome
states here becau
dwell restrained by the restraint of the
patimoka accomplished in good conduct and proper
accomplished in good conduct and proper
resort
seeing danger in the slightest faults
having undertaken the training rules
training them
when bicker you dwell restrained in such
a way
seeing the danger in slightest faults
then based upon
that virtue established upon virtue you
should develop the four
establishments establishments of
mindfulness
not before before that yeah so you're
doing your mindfulness before you even
accomplish yourself in precepts
it's just it goes against putting the
cart in front
expecting it to move
there's no way to have that type no no
well it's the same that's why it's
mindfulness samadhi it's the same
development same thing
it comes on the basis of established
uncompromised unbroken virtue
uncompromised yeah so how do you
uncompromise how do you know how do you
not compromise your virtue
by by overly defining your rules and
and sort of you know proliferating
aspects so by simply
not accepting any action that your mind
offers you out of
greed aversion delusion and you know
that and you know that
you know that am i acting out of
hindrances am i acting out of doubt am i acting out
am i acting out of doubt am i acting out
of restlessness
am i acting out of sensuality anger
sloth and laziness it's unwholesome if i
don't do it
i am accomplishing virtue so you will be
abandoning hindrances as well which is
what samadhi is
not acting out around wholesome states i
mean we speak about it so so
so often and all of that is contained
between you and your relationship with
your own virtue
or lack of it when i say lack of virtue
doesn't mean
you don't keep the precepts it means you
keep them but in that external
syllabus sense and you are not
internally becoming accomplished in
those rules
in other words you're not internalizing
criteria for unwholesome that you're
avoiding you're just adhering to the definition
you're just adhering to the definition
through your intellect
tradition authority and so on that if
you're not
you don't have the clarity that comes
from accomplishment
in virtue you cannot be mindful of the
body no no your mindfulness will be external
no no your mindfulness will be external
in the same sense
your responsibility for your virtues is
external so when you do mindfulness you'll be
so when you do mindfulness you'll be
doing it on the level of objects of your
senses which is not mindfulness
will be like a duty that's exactly what
meditation technique is for people
it's often taken in a sense of another
external duty that i must do
and it certainly always taken on the
level of sense objects
observations uh nimitas and whatever
else movements motions it's never taken as
movements motions it's never taken as
the internal expectations
recitations mantras visualization
visualizations yeah every that and that's why it's
yeah every that and that's why it's
taken there because there's no basis for
mindfulness no sufficient basis for mindfulness to
no sufficient basis for mindfulness to
be taken on the right peripheral
sufficiently peripheral context so what
happens then it's just you take it where
your mind is and your mind is out there
on the external things because you want
to avoid doubt in all these things
you're just adhering to
external things with a sense of duty
syllabus
and then your meditation becomes on the
level of that syllabus
and then your discernment is on that
level in other words it's only discernment
in other words it's only discernment
you're discerning things more on the
level of sense object without having
the right context the right basis for it
all because you haven't allowed yourself
to become accomplished in that virtue
correctly you haven't taken it up you haven't
you haven't taken it up you haven't
accepted the weight of responsibility
for it
and endured it
you